A Finding Aid to the William Ordway Partridge Papers, 1879-1920, 1957, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
William Ordway Partridge papers
1879-1920
1957
Archives of American Art
Partridge, William Ordway, 1861-1930
AAA.partwill
Archival Resource Key
0.2 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor, author, and poet, William Ordway Partridge, who was active in New York City and Washington, D.C., measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1879-1920, and 1957. This small collection consists primarily of letters to Partridge from artists, political figures, art historians, and authors; drafts and typescripts of Partridge's poems; and two clippings about Partridge's sculpture.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of the collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Biographical / Historical
Parisian-born sculptor, author, and poet, William Ordway Partridge (1861-1930) was known for his sculptures of famous writers, artists, political figures, and poets.
Partridge attended Adelphi Academy and Columbia College in New York and then traveled abroad to study in Florence, Rome, and Paris. He exhibited at the Paris Salon in his early twenties before returning to New York to focus on sculpture, lecturing, poetry reading, and writing and publishing his own poetry and articles on art. In addition to busts of writers and artists and many distinguished New York figures, he executed a large bronze of Alexander Hamilton in Prospect Park, Brooklyn.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 1965 by Mrs. Jacob B. Shohan, and in 2019 by Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr., art historians and collectors in Milford, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Contents
The papers of sculptor, author, and poet, William Ordway Partridge, who was active in New York City and Washington, D.C., measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1879-1920, and 1957. This small collection consists primarily of letters to Partridge from artists, political figures, art historians, and authors; drafts and typescripts of Partridge's poems; and two clippings about Partridge's sculpture.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection was digitized in 2019 and is available on the Archives of American Art website.
Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Poets -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- Washington (D.C.); McGuigan, Mary K.; McGuigan, John F., Jr. (John Fuller)
- William Ordway Partridge Papers, 1879-1920; 1957; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet
  Arrangement
  The papers are arranged by material type. Letters to Partridge are arranged alphabetically. Unless otherwise noted, all senders wrote 1 letter each.
  Scope and Contents
  Letters to Partridge mainly relate to Partridge's sculpture, invitations to events, and responses to invitations sent by Partridge. They include requests to visit his studio and view works in progress. Also found are two letters from Robert C. Winthrop, and Samuel Timmins to others which were probably collected by Partridge for the autographs of Winthrop and Timmins. Additional correspondents are noted in the container listing.
  Writings by Partridge include loose drafts of his poems and a typescript for a book of a collection of his poems. Writings by others include a draft of an essay "The Actor's Profession" and galley proofs of an untitled poem by Henry Austin, dedicated to James Gillespie Blaine. One news clipping from 1891 relates to Partridge's statue of Alexander Hamilton; another from 1957 recounts the discovery of two busts by Partridge during the demolition of the Manhattan Storage and Warehouse building.
  - Egyptian Passport, circa 1890; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters Collected by Partridge, 1879; 1885; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Partridge, A-C, 1882-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes letters from Abraham Archibald Anderson, Paul Wayland Bartlett, Edwin Howland Blashfield, Cyrus Townsend Brady, Edward C. Caswell (illustrated), Franklin B. Clark, Thomas Shields Clarke, and Royal Cortissoz.
  - Letters to Partridge, D-F, 1902-1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes letters from Frank Edwin Elwell and Daniel Chester French.
  - Letters to Partridge, G-L, 1894-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes letters from Leandro-Ramon Garrido, Jennie D. Garrison of the Pocahontas Memorial Association, John La Farge, and George Thomas Little regarding the purchase of Partridge's bronze Bust of Admiral Perry.
  - Letters to Partridge, M-P, 1896-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes letters from Henry Mosler, National Academy of Design, and National Arts Club.
  - Letters to Partridge, R-W, 1894-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes 2 letters from Corinne Roosevelt Robinson regarding Bust of Theodore Roosevelt (her brother), Charles H. Sherrill, Marie Peary Stafford regarding bust of her father and discoverer of the North Pole Admiral Robert E. Peary, Edmund Clarence Stedman, and Tertius Van Dyke regarding Partridge's bust of Henry van Dyke.
  - Manuscripts by Partridge, circa 1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts by Partridge, Book of Poems, 1883-1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings by Other, 1893; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 1891-1894; 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)